瓦雷利亚末日
伊耿一世（AC1-37 在位）
“征服者”
镶嵌红宝石的瓦雷利亚钢王冠
坦格利安家族征服维斯特洛
雷妮丝
伊耿一世的妹妹和妻子
伊尼斯一世（AC37-42 在位）
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
杰赫里斯一世（AC48-103 在位）
“和解者”“人瑞王”
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
杰赫里斯一世（AC48-103 在位）
“和解者”“人瑞王”
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
亚莉珊（AC36-100）
“善良王后”
杰赫里斯一世的妹妹和妻子
贝尔隆（AC57-101）
“勇敢的”“春晓王子”
杰赫里斯一世的儿子和国王之手
阿莱莎（AC60-84）
贝尔隆的妹妹和妻子
戴蒙
“浪荡王子”
贝尔隆的儿子 韦赛里斯一世的弟弟
科利斯·瓦列利安
“海蛇”“潮汛之主”
雷妮丝
“无冕女王”
韦赛里斯一世的堂姐
兰娜尔·瓦列利安（AC100- ）
科利斯和雷妮丝的女儿
奥托·海塔尔
韦赛里斯一世的国王之手
韦赛里斯一世（AC103开始在位至今）
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
阿莉森·海塔尔
奥托的女儿 韦赛里斯一世的第二任妻子
韦赛里斯一世（AC103开始在位至今）
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
爱玛·艾林（AC82-112）
韦赛里斯一世的表妹和第一任妻子
奥托·海塔尔
韦赛里斯一世的国王之手
阿莉森·海塔尔
奥托的女儿 韦赛里斯一世的第二任妻子
雷妮拉
韦赛里斯一世的女儿和王储
改编自 《血与火：坦格利安王朝史》
[美] 乔治·马丁 著
龙 王 家 族
第一季 第三集
伊耿二世 Second of His Name
此旗帜上的海马为瓦列利安家族的族徽。
克拉哈斯·达哈尔
“螃蟹喂食者” 三城同盟会司令
瓦列利安家族会找你算账的！
House Velaryon is coming for you!
海蛇会砍下你那该死的麻脸脑袋！
The Sea Snake will have your poxy fucking head!
不……不要啊！
No... no!
求你了！不！
No! Please!
去死吧 达哈尔亲王
Fuck you, Prince Drahar.
日你婊子老母！日你杂种老爹！
Fuck your whore mother and bastard father!
操！
Fuck!
不要啊！
No!
不
No.
弓箭手！
Optyssys!
戴蒙王子万岁！
Hail, Prince Daemon!
烧死这帮天杀的三城同盟会杂种！
Burn the fucking Triarchy cunts alive!
王子 我在这里！
Here, my prince!
救我！
Save me!
科拉克休
戴蒙的龙
- 直接回洞里去！  - 快回洞里！快！
- Direct to the caves! - To the caves! Now!
撤退！撤到洞里面！
Retreat! Retreat to the caves!
快回洞里！
Back to the caves!
戴蒙·坦格利安
“浪荡王子” 韦赛里斯的弟弟
你在哪？
Where are you?
出来面对我 达哈尔！
Come out and face me, Drahar!
快滚出来 达哈尔！
Come out, Drahar!
人躲哪里去了？
Where are you?
我要把你喂给你自己的螃蟹！
I'm gonna feed you to your own crabs!
你人呢？
Where are you?
他的头发像您 陛下
He has your hair, Your Grace.
- 他的头发确实像我 - 他的眼睛也像您 陛下
- He does have my hair. - He has your eyes, Your Grace.
说得没错
Yes, he does.
你的鼻子也很像我 是不是呀？
And you have my nose, don't you?
刚刚两岁 这孩子就已经生得一副帝王相了
Two years old and already our boy has a kingly presence.
或许吧 哥哥 不过今天早晨
He may yet, brother but this morning he insisted
奥托·海塔尔
国王之手
他非要用手喝粥
on eating porridge with his hands.
霍巴特·海塔尔
南境灯塔 学城守护者 旧镇之音 奥托的哥哥
他会长大的
He will grow.
都是因为他 这么多人聚集于此
We've quite a party assembled in his honor.
当然这次狩猎结束后 我们就有更多值得庆祝的事了
And surely by the end of this hunt, we shall have more to celebrate.
您说 有什么值得庆祝的事呢？
And what is that, pray tell?
这是伊耿的第二个命名日 他已经不再是小婴儿了
It is Aegon's second name day. His infancy's behind him.
就等韦赛里斯指定他为铁王座的继承人了
It only remains for Viserys to name him heir to the throne.
我可没这么确定
I wouldn't be so sure.
他是国王的长子
He's the king's firstborn son.
我觉得陛下还没有认清这件事
I don't know that His Grace sees it so clearly.
那就靠你来让他看清了……
Then it lies with you to make him see it...
首相大人
Lord Hand.
陛下
Your Grace.
泰兰·兰尼斯特
海政大臣
我从石阶列岛带来了急报
I bring urgent news from the Stepstones.
韦赛里斯·坦格利安一世
国王
阿莉森·海塔尔
王后 奥托之女
螃蟹喂食者被围困在血石岛后躲了起来
The Crabfeeder has dug in for siege on Bloodstone
同时他的部下趁着夜色摧毁我们的舰队
while his men sabotage our fleet under cover of dark.
泰兰 今天别提这个
Not today, Tyland.
只怕石阶列岛的事情万分火急
The matter at the Stepstones is regrettably urgent.
已经开战三年了 再等三天也无妨
It's been three years. It can wait another three days.
来吧……吃点东西
Come... eat.
弥补赶路的辛苦
Fortify yourselves for the journey.
别客气
Please.
莱昂诺·斯壮
法务大臣
补给车队准备好了吗？
Is the baggage train ready?
现在正在临河门集结
It is presently massing at the River Gate.
杰森公爵希望我们中午前抵达御林
Lord Jason expects us in the Kingswood before midday.
- 你看见雷妮拉了吗？ - 没看到 陛下
- Have you seen Rhaenyra? - I have not, Your Grace.
三城同盟会的人躲进血石岛的洞穴
With the Triarchy now sheltering in Bloodstone's caves
龙的威胁大大降低了
the threat of the dragons is blunted.
他们没有步兵吗？
They don't have foot soldiers?
他们的雇佣兵已经陆续撤离了 陛下
But their sellswords have been withdrawing in droves, Your Grace.
就连他们也看得出这是场必败的战斗
Even the mercenaries can see that it is a losing effort.
雷妮拉在哪里？
Where's Rhaenyra?
克里斯顿·科尔
雷妮拉·坦格利安的护卫
我也不确定 陛下
I cannot be sure at present, Your Grace.
瓦列利安家族的军队消耗很严重 陛下
The Velaryon forces have suffered heavy attrition, Your Grace.
士兵之间已经怨声载道了
The seeds of dissent are sown amongst the rank and file.
戴蒙用兵太严苛
Daemon has driven the men hard.
士兵们开始质疑他的命令了
They have begun to question his command.
如果国王打算干预此事的话……
If the crown were ever to intervene...
- 泰兰 - 现在是时候了
- Tyland. - now is the time.
戴蒙和海蛇未经陛下准许就擅自开战
Daemon and the Sea Snake started their war without His Grace's leave.
都过了这么久 如果国王现在干预
Were he to intervene now, after so long
会让我们显得软弱
it would make the crown appear weak.
七层地狱啊 谁能告诉我
Can someone tell me
雷妮拉到底在哪？
where in the Seven Hells Rhaenyra might be?
在巨龙眼皮底下
Under the dragon's eye
雷妮拉·坦格利安
龙石岛公主 王储
在巨龙眼皮底下
Under the dragon's eye
再来一遍
Again.
或许公主想听些别的歌谣？
Perhaps the Princess might like to hear something else?
不想 再唱一遍
She would not. Play it again.
她带着舰队和子民逃离
She fled with her ships And her people
心碎只为那……
Her heart broken for those...
王后陛下
Your Grace.
我说停了吗？
Did I say to stop?
从头再来
From the beginning.
她带着舰队
She fled with her ships
- 和子民逃离 - 雷妮拉？
- And her people - Rhaenyra?
怎么了 王后陛下？
Yes, my Queen?
大家都在外庭等你呢
Your presence is wanted in the outer courtyard.
王室狩猎马上要出发了
The royal hunt readies to depart.
我决定还是留在这读书
I have decided to remain here and read instead.
你可以走了 山姆威尔
You may go, Samwell.
公主命令你留下来
You are to stay by order of the Princess.
王后命令你立刻离开神木林
The Queen commands you to leave the Godswood at once.
告辞了 公主
Princess.
王后陛下
Your Grace.
国王希望你可以加入我们
The King wishes for you to join us.
国王有很多值得庆祝的事 用不着我去
The King has much to celebrate. He does not need me.
他想要我们一起去
He wants for us all to be together.
或许狩猎会很有趣
Perhaps the hunt could be fun.
这是国王的命令吗？
Is it the King's command?
- 是 不过…… - 那现在就走 王后陛下
- Yes, but it... - Then at once, Your Grace.
也不用这样的
But it needn't be.
说真的 我们大可不必如此 雷妮拉
None of it needs be this way, in truth, Rhaenyra.
看 这样不是挺好吗？
Well, isn't this splendid?
我们全家外出庆祝
The whole of our family off to celebration
并在御林中探险
and adventure in the Kingswood.
你现在这样适合外出吗？
Should you be traveling in such condition?
学士们说出来亲近大自然会有好处
The maesters said that being out in nature would do me well.
迟早你也会有你自己的孩子
You'll be with your own child, sooner than late
让我成为一个骄傲的外公
and make me a proud grandsire.
也没那么糟糕
It's not so bad.
怀孕是有点久 不过伊耿出生得很快
The days are long but Aegon came quickly
也没遇到什么麻烦
and without fuss.
今天你应该和我一同骑马外出
You should ride out with me today.
参加围猎
Join in the chase.
我不想
I'd rather not.
野猪在被猎杀的时候叫得像小孩子一样
The boars squeal like children when they're being slaughtered.
我不怎么喜欢
I find it discomforting.
这只是狩猎 雷妮拉
It's a hunt, Rhaenyra.
你想怎么参与?
How would you like to participate?
我也不知道为什么叫我去
I'm not sure why I'm asked.
因为你是我女儿 是公主
Because you are my daughter. The Princess.
所以你肩负责任
And you have duties.
所以我时刻被提醒这些
As I am ceaselessly reminded.
- 什么？ - 所以我时刻都被提醒这些
- I'm sorry? - As I am ceaselessly reminded.
如果你积极参与的话就不需要提醒了
You wouldn't need to be reminded if you ever attended to them.
没人是为我而来的
No one's here for me.
霍巴特·海塔尔
南境灯塔 学城守护者 旧镇之音 奥托的哥哥
万岁 万岁
Hail, hail, Aegon
征服者伊耿宝宝 二世！
the Conqueror-Babe, Second of His Name!
我是说殿下的第二个命名日！
Here's to His Grace on his second name day!
有消息说乔汉娜小姐被拐走了
Lady Johanna was reported to have been abducted
就在史文大人的船经过石阶列岛的时候
when one of Lord Swann's ships sailed through the Stepstones.
那乔汉娜小姐会怎么样？
What will happen to Lady Johanna?
她会被卖到自由城邦的青楼里
She's to be sold to a pillow house in the Free Cities
如果谣言是真的话
if you believe the rumors.
恐怕众神没把我造得适合狩猎
I fear the gods did not make me for hunting.
- 我能与你们同坐吗 夫人们？  - 当然 一起坐吧
- Might I sit with you, my ladies? - Of course, please join us.
这位是拉里斯·斯壮 我们法务大臣莱昂诺的小儿子
Larys Strong, the youngest son of our master of laws, Lord Lyonel.
我夫君说还没有国王能
My lord husband says that no king has ever been able
长久地驯服石阶列岛
to tame the Stepstones for long.
那就是一片不毛之地 只适合野蛮人
It's an inhospitable place, suited only for savages.
或许公主殿下可以给我们讲讲
Perhaps the Princess can give us some insight.
哦 我不知道怎么说 我从没去过石阶列岛
Oh, I'm not sure how I could. I've never been to the Stepstones.
你亲爱的叔叔是这场战争背后的主使 是吗？
Your dear uncle is the great mind behind this war, is he not?
我不知道 我已经很多年没跟戴蒙说过话了
I wouldn't know. I have not spoken to Daemon in years.
自从你取代他成为王位继承人之后吧
Since you supplanted him as heir.
戴蒙自己做出的选择 凯拉夫人
Daemon made his choices, Lady Ceira.
公主更适合成为继承人
The Princess was more suited to the role.
他弄得一团糟 国王必须出面解决
He's made a mess and the King must put an end to it.
派出舰队和士兵 把三城同盟会清理干净
Send fleets and men, and clear out the Triarchy for good.
但是国王没有参战
But the crown is not at war.
王国已经参战了 公主
The crown is at war, Princess
虽然你父亲不肯承认
though your father refuses to admit it.
我们已经被你叔叔和海蛇拖进战争了
We've been dragged into it by your uncle and the Sea Snake.
那么您又是如何报效王国的呢 雷德温夫人？
And how have you served the realm of late, Lady Redwyne?
吃蛋糕吗？
By eating cake?
我很好奇 公主
I wonder, Princess
您的第二个命名日也有这么气派吗？
was your own second name day as grand as this?
说实话我一点也不记得了 伊耿也不会记得
I honestly don't recall and neither will Aegon.
我是杰森·兰尼斯特公爵
Lord Jason Lannister.
看到这么多狮子就猜到了
I gathered that from all the lions.
我们应该没有正式见过
I don't think we've been properly introduced.
您的双胞胎弟弟是我父亲的御前会议成员
Your twin serves on my father's council.
泰兰这个人...
Tyland is...
十分迟钝 诸神保佑他
frightfully dull, Gods love him.
这会是你尝过的最好的蜜酒
The finest honeyed wine you'll ever taste.
- 当然 是兰尼斯港产的  - 当然
- Made in Lannisport, of course. - Of course.
御林 真是个好猎场
The Kingswood, it's a fine hunting ground.
但是最好的地方在凯岩城 我家附近
But the best spot is to be found at Casterly Rock, near my home.
你去过吗？
Have you been?
旅行时去过一次 小时候和我母亲一起
Once. On tour, with my mother when I was young.
说实话我也不怎么记得了
And honestly can't recall much of that either.
凯岩城的高度是旧镇参天塔的三倍
The Rock is thrice the height of the Hightower in Oldtown.
甚至比北境的绝境长城还高
Taller still than the Wall in the north.
据说如果天气足够好的话
It's been said that if one were to stand in the tower
站在塔顶能清楚地看到日落之海对岸
on a perfect day, one could see clear across the Sunset Sea.
那肯定很壮观
It must be quite something.
当然 我们没有龙穴 不过...
We don't have a Dragonpit, of course, but...
我有办法和资源能够建造一个
I do have the means and resources to build one.
你为什么要建龙穴？
Why would you need a Dragonpit?
当然是为了给龙安家
To house dragons, of course.
我会为了我的女王做任何事
I'd do anything for my Queen...
或者...为了夫人
or... lady wife.
感谢你的酒
Thank you for the wine.
这就是我对于你的价值？
Is that what I am to you?
给大贵族的奖赏？
A prize to proffer about to the great houses?
你到年龄了 雷妮拉
You're of age, Rhaenyra.
杰森·兰尼斯特是位佳偶
Jason Lannister is an excellent match.
他傲慢又自我
He's arrogant and self-serious.
那我以为你们在这方面倒是挺像
Well, I thought you might have that in common.
自从你成年以来
Since you came of age
全国各地的来信像河流汇集成湖
I've been slowly drowning in a lake of parchment
慢慢地快把我淹死了
flowing from every corner of the realm.
全是在提亲
Marriage proposals, all.
而且我多次试着跟你讨论这件事
And I have tried, often, to discuss it with you
可你每次都拒绝我
but you've refused me at every turn.
那是因为我不想结婚
That is because I do not wish to get married.
连我都必须屈服于传统和职责 雷妮拉！
Even I do not exist above tradition and duty, Rhaenyra!
打扰了 陛下
Excuse me, Your Grace.
你必须嫁人
You must marry.
- 什么事？ - 王家猎手有消息
- Yes? - The royal huntsman
需要汇报 陛下
has sent a report, Your Grace.
有人目击到一头白色的雄鹿
There's been a sighting of a white hart.
那头鹿是御林之王 陛下
The stag is the king of the Kingswood, Your Grace.
一个献给伊耿王子命名日的帝王之兆
A regal portent for Prince Aegon's name day.
公主
Princess.
公主 等等！
Princess, wait!
公主 慢下来！
Princess, slow down!
公主！
Princess!
出什么事了？
What happened back there?
我的父亲
My father.
想把我卖给杰森·兰尼斯特
Trying to sell me off to Jason Lannister.
是...
Was...
是不是我被册封为铁王座的继承人
was I named heir to the Iron Throne
只是为了用我来进一步提升
so that I might only further raise the standing
凯岩城公爵的地位？
of a lord of Casterly Rock?
您想让我杀了他吗？
You want me to kill him?
我们应该返回营地 公主
We should return to camp, Princess.
今天天气不错
It's a beautiful day.
我们应该逛逛御林
We should take in the Kingswood.
你订过婚吗 克里斯顿爵士？
Were you ever betrothed, Ser Criston?
我当然也曾是个热衷冒险的青年
I had an adventurous youth
那时我父亲在黑港侍奉
when my father served at Blackhaven, to be sure.
但是我的地位还够不上一门正式的婚约
But my station was never high enough for a formal betrothal.
在我宣誓成为御林铁卫之前
Before I spoke my vows as a knight of the Kingsguard
如果我想的话 可能会娶一个平民女孩
I could have married a common-born girl had I wish.
你能为自己的人生做主 真幸运
How lucky you are to have a say in your own life.
王国里很多人愿意您交换位置 公主
Many in the realm would gladly trade positions with you, Princess.
那只是因为他们不在我这个位置罢了
Only because none of them has ever held my position.
我虽然是龙石岛的公主 但却没有实权
I may be the Princess of Dragonstone, but I am toothless.
从前
One day
没几年前
not so long ago...
是您的权力把我的名字写进了白典
you held enough power to write my name into the White Book.
让您父亲册封我为御林铁卫
When your father named me to his Kingsguard
这是科尔家族从未有过的最高荣誉
it was the highest honor any Cole had ever known.
我所拥有的一切都是您给的
All that I have, I owe to you.
所以我可不认为您没有实权 公主
Now I'd hardly call that toothless, Princess.
- 陛下  - 还有多远?
- Your Grace. - How far?
我们在东边半里格的地方发现它的粪便
The droppings were found half a league to the east.
- 还是新鲜的  - 是两三小时前的 陛下
- Still fresh. - Between two and three hours, Your Grace.
我最好的探子看到它了
My best scout spied him.
这野兽重达35石 现在我们已经找到了它的踪迹
The beast is upward of 35 stone, and we now have his trail.
- 是啊 - 在巨龙统治维斯特洛之前
- Aye. - Before the dragons ruled over Westeros
白鹿才是这片土地上王室的象征
the white hart was the symbol of royalty in these lands.
而且偏偏是在今天……
And on this day, of all days...
我从不迷信预兆 陛下
I've never been one for signs and portents, Your Grace
但如果诸神真的愿意表示眷顾……
but if the gods did wish to show their favor...
陛下
Your Grace.
这是我家黄金长廊
I had this forged in the Golden Gallery
为伊耿王子打造的
in honor of Prince Aegon.
真是个好东西
It's quite a thing.
希望能用它给白鹿
I hope it might provide the killing stroke
刺出致命一击
against your white hart.
御林之王
King of the Kingswood.
好像七神也祝福了这一天
It's as if the Seven themselves have blessed this day.
感谢你的慷慨
Thank you for your generosity.
如果能娶雷妮拉公主为妻
I would be honored...
我将十分荣幸
to take the Princess Rhaenyra to wife
陛下
Your Grace.
我能为您
What I offer you
为王室和您女儿提供力量
the crown and your daughter, is strength.
你觉得坦格利安家族还需要力量吗?
Do you think that House Targaryen wants for strength?
如果有人能够给您更多龙 您不要吗?
If someone offered you more dragons, would you not take them?
你能给我龙吗?
Do you have dragons to offer?
凯岩城是个富丽堂皇的地方
Casterly Rock is a splendid seat.
雷妮拉坐在我身边不会丢脸
Rhaenyra may take her place there by my side without shame
也能很好地弥补她身份地位的损失
and feel herself well-compensated for her loss in station.
她的身份地位有什么损失?
What loss of station?
如果您要册封小伊耿为继承人 陛下
If you were to name young Aegon heir, Your Grace.
我什么时候说要这样做了?
And when would I be doing that?
我只是以为……
I had assumed...
毕竟他是您的长子 我们很多人都认为……
As he is your firstborn son, many of us had assumed...
你说“我们很多人”
"Many of us," you say.
你的封臣质疑我对继承人的选择了吗?
Have your bannermen questioned my choice of heir?
-  当然没有 陛下  - 如果有此等叛乱
- Of course not, Your Grace. - It is your sworn duty
你有责任上报给我
to report rebellion stirring in my kingdom.
叛乱? 没有这种事 陛下
Rebellion? There has been nothing of the sort, Your Grace.
-  我只是……  - 我不是一时兴起
- I was only... - I did not decide to name Rhaenyra
才决定册封雷妮拉为继承人
my heir on a whim.
王国里所有领主都最好牢记这点
All the lords of the kingdom would do well to remember that.
感谢你的礼物
Thank you for the gift.
陛下
Your Grace.
上酒
Wine.
猎人发现踪迹了 陛下
The huntsman has the trail, Your Grace
已经派出了猎犬
and has sent out the hounds.
白鹿很快就会被逼入绝境了
It won't be long now until the white hart is cornered.
您的猎物唾手可得
Your prize is within reach.
您怎么看杰森大人的求婚?
What do you make of Lord Jason's proposal?
他真不是一般的傲慢
That man's pride has pride.
您不只是雷妮拉的父亲 您是国王
You're not only Rhaenyra's father, you're the King.
她会按照你的命令做的
She will do as you command.
我并不想命令她 奥托
It is not my wish to command her, Otto.
我只想让她快乐
I want her to be happy.
凯岩城之外还有一个选择
There is another choice, beyond Casterly Rock.
这个选择可能让你更好受些……
One perhaps you might be more comfortable with, one...
离家也更近些
closer to home.
你想的是谁？
Who do you have in mind?
伊耿王子
Prince Aegon.
这孩子才刚刚两岁 奥托
The boy just turned two, Otto.
是的 但这样就可以制止
Yes, but it would cease
那些络绎不绝向雷妮拉求婚的人了
the endless proposals for Rhaenyra's hand.
-  给他们订下婚约……  - 我是来狩猎的
- Betroth them... - I came here to hunt.
不是来被这堆该死的政治游戏逼到窒息的
Not to be suffocated by all this fucking politicking.
那就不提这个了
Let us speak no more of it.
已经派人去找雷妮拉了 陛下
We've sent out riders to find Rhaenyra, Your Grace.
克里斯顿爵士跟着她呢
Ser Criston went after her
希望他们正在一起
so the hope is that they are together.
这姑娘太叛逆了
The girl is a heedless contrarian.
如果我反过来不准她嫁去兰尼斯特
If I instead forbade her to wed a Lannister
她一定会因为怨恨而跟杰森大人私奔
she would have run off with Lord Jason out of spite.
我真是个了不起的坦格利安国王啊
A truly great Targaryen king I am.
对自己十七岁的女儿感到无能为力
Powerless over mine own daughter of seven-and-ten.
杰赫里斯国王和平统治了半个世纪
King Jaehaerys ruled over half a century of peace
但孩子们快把他逼疯了
while his children drove him to the edge of madness.
尤其是女儿
His daughters in particular.
这是……传统 陛下
It is... tradition, Your Grace.
关于这件事 你想听听我的建议吗？
Do you wish to hear my opinion on the matter?
我猜一下？
Should I guess?
你认为你儿子 “碎骨人”哈尔温
You believe that your son, Ser Harwin Breakbones
七大王国最强壮的骑士
the strongest knight in the Seven Kingdoms
是雷妮拉最合适的人选
is the best match for Rhaenyra.
您抬举我了 陛下 但这不是我想说的
You flatter me, Your Grace, but no.
我认为最适合雷妮拉的人
It would seem to me the best match for Rhaenyra
是“海蛇”的儿子
is the son of the Sea Snake
兰尼诺爵士
Ser Laenor.
几年前 我建议你娶他姐姐为妻
Some years ago, I counseled you to take his sister to wife.
如今理由依然相同
My reasoning remains the same.
兰尼诺有纯正的瓦雷利亚血统
Laenor is of pure Valyrian descent.
他有您堂姐雷妮丝公主的血脉
He shares blood with your cousin, the Princess Rhaenys
他是王国内最富有家族的继承人
and he is the heir to the wealthiest house in the realm.
您两家的的裂痕
The breach between your houses
自我上次提起 至今也未见愈合的迹象
has not narrowed since I last spoke of it.
这样会大大减少外界对科利斯大人
It would do much to assuage Lord Corlys
或真或假的种种轻视
of any slights, real or imagined.
当然 我们得祈祷
We must pray, of course
兰尼诺能在石阶列岛战事中活下来
that Laenor survives the fighting in the Stepstones.
公主 我必须最后一次请求您返回营地
Princess, I must make a final plea that we return to the camp.
我更想呆在这
I rather prefer it here.
陛下一定非常担心您的缺席
His Grace is certain to be worried by your absence.
陛下要这么爱担心那就担心死吧
His Grace can worry himself to death if he so likes.
和我说说吧 克里斯顿爵士
Tell me something, Ser Criston.
你认为王国的臣民最终能接受我成为他们的女王吗？
Do you think the realm will ever accept me as their Queen?
臣民除了接受别无选择 公主
They'll have no choice but to, Princess.
您还好么 陛下？
Is everything all right, Your Grace?
你也知道 我……
You know, I...
我立她为王储是防止戴蒙荼毒王国
I named her to protect the realm from Daemon.
那时她是我唯一的孩子
She was my only child.
王国之光
The Realm's Delight.
我立她是出于爱……
I named her out of love...
因为我当时不再相信……
because I no longer believed...
不再相信什么了 亲爱的？
Believed what, my love?
我的很多先祖都是驭龙者
Many in my line have been dragonriders.
还有极少数是梦行者
Very few among us have been Dreamers.
龙的力量跟预言的力量相比算什么？
What is the power of a dragon next to the power of prophecy?
- 时辰很晚了 夫君 - 雷妮拉很小的时候……
- The hour is too late, husband. - When Rhaenyra was a child...
我做过一个梦
I saw it in a dream.
我看到了 真切得像这篝火一样
As vivid as these flames, I saw it.
我的妻子产下一名男婴
A male babe, born to me
头戴征服者的王冠
wearing the Conqueror's crown.
我太希望这梦能成真
I so wanted it to be true.
希望自己也是个梦行者
To be a Dreamer myself.
我企图重现那个梦 夜复一夜
I sought that vision again, night after night
但它再也没出现过
but it never came again.
我把心思和意念都倾注在它上面
I poured all my thought and will into it
我的魔怔最终害死了雷妮拉的母亲
and my obsession killed Rhaenyra's mother.
韦赛里斯
Viserys.
我以为雷妮拉能带我走出悲伤和悔恨的深渊
I thought Rhaenyra was the way out of my abyss of grief and regret.
把她立为继承人能让一切恢复如初
That naming her heir would begin to set things right.
- 一切都恢复了！ - 我没想过要续弦
- Oh, it did! - I never imagined I would remarry.
没想过真能有个儿子
That I would have a son.
万一我错了呢？
What if I was wrong?
陛下 虽然不是白鹿 但也是个大家伙
It may not be white, Your Grace, but he's a big lad.
陛下
Your Grace.
请用它
For the kill.
往这刺 陛下
Strike here, Your Grace.
陛下 再来一次 往您的左手边一点
One more time, Your Grace. A bit to your left.
别
No.
来吧 王子乖乖 让陛下消停一会
Come, sweet prince. Let's give Her Grace some peace.
殿下享受这次狩猎么？
Did you enjoy the hunt, Your Grace?
还行吧
Well enough.
我外孙过得好吗？
How fared my grandson?
兰尼斯特夫人和雷德温夫人可喜欢他了
The ladies Lannister and Redwyne were quite taken with him.
应该的
As they should be.
他是王国的未来
He's the future of the realm.
你自己也看到这次庆典的规模了
You yourself witnessed the scale of the celebration
大家多团结
how it's united the men.
你给国王生下儿子时
When you bore the King a son
十五年的疑虑都烟消云散了
you ended 15 years of uncertainty and doubt.
伊耿 人如其名 生来就是要统治七国的
Aegon, like his namesake, was born to rule the Seven Kingdoms.
如果韦赛里斯把他立为王储 举国会为他欢庆
If Viserys were to name him heir, the realm would fete him for it.
你不欢喜么？
Does this not please you?
你不希望儿子能当上国王么？
Do you not want your son to be king?
哪个母亲不想啊？
What mother wouldn't?
你不能无视确凿的事实
You mustn't ignore the certain truth
如果雷妮拉取代了伊耿称王
that if Rhaenyra were to step over Aegon to ascend the throne
王国就会分崩离析
the realm would tear itself apart.
各大家族已经向她宣誓效忠了 咱们家也一样
They all swore obeisance to her, our house among them.
那是伊耿出生之前
That was before Aegon.
雷妮拉会是个好女王
Rhaenyra will be a good Queen.
她就算是杰赫里斯再世也没用的
It wouldn't matter if she were Jaehaerys himself born again.
雷妮拉是女人
Rhaenyra is a woman.
你把我儿子当什么？
What of my son?
你想让我把他抚养成一个篡夺姐姐的天赐权利的人么？
Would you have me raise a man to steal his own sister's birthright?
伊耿才是被夺权的那个
It is Aegon that's being robbed.
他是国王的长子
He's the firstborn son of the King.
否认他对铁王座的继承权
To deny that he is heir to the throne
就是蔑视诸神和世人的律法
is to assail the laws of gods and men.
我们的前路并不确定 但结局很明确
The road ahead is uncertain, but the end is clear.
伊耿会成为国王
Aegon will be King.
你要引导韦赛里斯恢复理智
You must guide Viserys towards reason.
他自己想不明白的
He'll never find it on his own.
你还好么 夫君？
How are you feeling, husband?
诸神在惩罚我过分享受了
The gods have punished me for my indulgences.
- 至少说明确实是好酒 - 好过头了
- At least the wine was good. - Too good.
我希望咱们能讨论些事情
I was hoping we might discuss something.
雷妮拉的事么？
Rhaenyra?
我觉得她不喜欢杰森·兰尼斯特作陪
I do not think she enjoyed Jason Lannister's company.
简直气死了
She is cross.
我警告过你啦
I warned you that she would be.
雷妮拉到岁数了
Rhaenyra has come of age.
她必须嫁给一位大领主 愿意敬她 护她
She must needs marry a high lord who will honor her, defend her
作为王夫服侍她
and serve her as king consort.
她想不想结婚根本不是重点
Her wishes in this matter are irrelevant.
我相信她会结婚的 陛下
I do believe that Rhaenyra will marry, Your Grace.
但得让她相信那是她自己的选择
But she must believe it is her choice to do so.
……允许他们投降，否则后果更糟糕
……许多人被蝇虫和老鼠放倒，健康的也是疲惫不堪。
……他们正在猛攻……我们需要人手……
……否则就会全盘皆输，都会死在沙滩上……
魏蒙德·瓦列利安
- 这是什么？ - 一封信
- What's this? - A letter.
魏蒙德·瓦列利安寄来的
From Vaemond Velaryon.
- 海蛇的弟弟？ - 对
- The Sea Snake's brother? - Yes.
他和残余的部队还在石阶列岛作战
He's fighting in the Stepstones with all the rest of them.
我能看看么？
May I?
科利斯大人和戴蒙王子快输了
Lord Corlys and Prince Daemon are losing their war.
据说战事非常不利
Badly, by all accounts.
这是在请求援助
This is a plea for aid.
那为何不援助呢？
Then why not send it?
因为发动战争的是两个异见者
Because it is a war started by two malcontents
他们对我的决策心怀不满
unhappy with decisions I made.
如果我现在给戴蒙和科利斯提供援军
If I now provide Daemon and Corlys succor
大家会怎么看待我这个国王？
what will that say of their King?
或许会说国王是个好人 很爱自己的弟弟
Perhaps that he is a good man who loves his brother.
嗯 你要是真这么想 亲爱的
Well, if you truly believe that, my dear
只能说明你心胸宽广
then you possess a generous spirit.
那你相信什么呢 韦赛里斯？
What do you believe, Viserys?
我觉得我就是个永远无法
That I am forever doomed to anger one person
取悦所有人的倒霉蛋
in the pleasing of another.
那我问个更简单的问题？
Then I pose a simpler question.
哪样更利于王国的稳定 是放任螃蟹喂食者壮大实力
Is it better for the realm if the Crabfeeder thrives
还是把他斩草除根？
or is vanquished?
即刻动身前往矮石 亚当爵士
Make haste to Dwarfstone, Ser Addam.
务必亲手将它交给戴蒙王子
Hand-deliver this to Prince Daemon yourself.
立刻去办 陛下
At once, Your Grace.
矮石？
Dwarfstone?
我给戴蒙送去消息 援兵正驶往石阶列岛
I'm sending word to Daemon. Aid is sailing to the Stepstones.
- 他有要求增援吗？ - 他宁愿战死
- Did he make call for help? - He would sooner die.
但是他的国王不允许那样
But his King does not mean to allow that.
你不觉得我的决定很正确吗？
Do you not think my decision correct?
正如我经常被提醒的那样 这和我的想法并无关系
It is no consequence to what I think, as I'm often reminded.
戴蒙就如深扎在我血肉里的刺
Daemon is thorn enough in my flesh.
你一定要学他吗？
Will you insist on taking after him?
每件事都必须争斗一番吗？
Must everything be a battle?
如果你指的是你想把我嫁到凯岩城……
If you refer to your attempt to marry me off to Casterly Rock...
我很抱歉 雷妮拉
I am sorry, Rhaenyra.
我试着去帮你 你领情吗？
I was trying to help you. Will you not be helped?
为什么在你身上的每一次努力都会遭到你的殊死抵抗？
Why must every effort on your behalf be resisted as if to the death?
因为你想换掉我
Because you mean to replace me.
让阿莉森·海塔尔的儿子换掉我 他是你一直梦寐以求的男丁
With Alicent Hightower's son. The boy you always wanted.
你现在已经拥他在手 我对你已经全然没有利用价值了
You have him in hand now, you have no further use for me.
你大可以把我兜售个好价钱
You might as well peddle me for what you can.
换一座山上的堡垒 一支庞大的舰队
A mountain stronghold or a fleet of ships.
你误解我了 雷妮拉
You have misjudged me, Rhaenyra.
人尽皆知
All know it.
杰森·兰尼斯特知道这事
Jason Lannister knows it.
你亲口说的
You said it yourself.
全境的领主们像秃鹫一样聚集到我的尸体上
The lords of the realm gather like vultures to a carcass
想要饱餐一顿
hoping to feast on my bones.
作为统治者我们确实需要为了利益来联姻
It is true that as rulers we must marry for advantage
去建立联盟增强实力
to forge alliances and bolster our strength.
你也一直深谙这点
You have always understood this.
我和你母亲订下婚事 那时才十……
I myself was promised to your mother when I was ten...
十七岁的年纪
Ten-and-seven years of age.
谷地有一支军队能与北境抗衡
The Vale had an army to rival the North.
我记事起就一直听那个故事了
I've heard that story since I've had ears to.
我深爱她
I loved her.
她让我成为了真正的男人
She made a man of me.
我不想让其他人取代你 孩子
I do not seek to replace you, child.
这几年你一直很孤独
You've been much alone these last few years
孤独又易怒
alone and angry.
我不会长生不老
I will not live forever.
我希望看到你生活富足 幸福美满
I wish to see you contented. Happy, even.
- 你觉得靠一个男人能办到？ - 是家庭
- You think a man will do it? - A family.
- 我曾有过家庭 - 你想要我做什么？
- I had a family. - What would you have me do?
如果真的是为了利益考虑 你当初就该迎娶兰娜尔·瓦列利安！
If it was for advantage, you would have wed Laena Velaryon!
你说的没错
That is true enough.
你必须结婚
You must marry.
加强你的继承人地位
Strengthen your own claim.
巩固你的继承权 赶紧生孩子
Shore up your succession. Multiply.
至于你的良配……
As to your match...
你自己选
make it yourself.
找到他
Search him out.
找一个你喜欢的
Find one that pleases you.
就像我那样
As I did.
雷妮拉
Rhaenyra.
我的确动摇过
I did waver.
有那么一阵
At one time.
但我现在以你母亲的名义向你发誓
But I swear to you now, on your mother's memory
你不会被取代
you will not be supplanted.
我们有16艘 或许18艘适航的船只
We have 16, perhaps 18, seaworthy ships.
700名步兵 约60名骑士
700 foot, some 60 knights.
粮草消耗很快
Our food quickly dwindles
尽管能从海中补充些渔获
save for what we can fish from the sea.
我想还能坚持两周
I would say we have a fortnight
也许在严格的配给管理下能再久些
mayhaps a bit longer with strict rationing.
我已经求助潮头岛派更多的船
I've made call for Driftmark to send more ships
但还要几周才能到
but they will be weeks away.
我军的势头正在衰弱 三城同盟会知道这点
We are faltering and the Triarchy knows it.
我们必须加紧进攻 继续派出龙
We must press the attack. Continue sending the dragons.
这是徒劳的 父亲
It's pointless, Father.
螃蟹喂食者把住了咽喉要道
The Crabfeeder's created a chokepoint here
魏蒙德·瓦列利安
科利斯的弟弟
就在这些沙丘后方
beyond these dunes.
兰尼诺·瓦列利安
科利斯的儿子
弓箭手占据高地 步兵占据平地
Archers hold the high positions, foot soldiers hold the ground.
科利斯·瓦列利安
“海蛇”“潮汛之主” 潮头岛伯爵
我们一次又一次地在龙背上扫射
We strafe them on dragonback again and again
但他们只是撤退到洞穴里
but they just retreat within the caves.
龙们可以在血石上盘旋 直到它们从天上下来
Dragons can circle Bloodstone until they fall out of the sky.
螃蟹喂食者和他的人没有理由离开洞穴
The Crabfeeder and his men have no reason to leave those caves.
我们必须给他们一个理由
We must give them one.
一块引诱螃蟹的肉
An offering of flesh to bait the crab.
谁？
Who?
龙回来了！
Dragon returning!
没错 谁？
Yes, who?
这里有谁愿意欣然赴死？
Which man here will happily go to his death?
侄儿 让我看看哪个骑士会慷慨下地狱？
Show me the knight who will march into that hellpit
我让你看看疯子是什么样子
nephew, and I will show you a madman.
- 戴蒙 - 戴蒙是我们失败的原因
- Daemon. - Daemon is why we are losing.
他至少还在打仗
He at least is fighting this war.
叔叔 你在这个议会中扮演了什么角色？
What role have you played in this council, Uncle?
- 除了当抱怨大臣 还有吗？ - 够了 兰尼诺
- Other than master of complaints? - Enough, Laenor.
如果君临不支援戴蒙
If King's Landing will not support Daemon
我们为什么要这样做？
why should any of us?
管你是不是我的血亲 魏蒙德 我不会让你煽动叛乱
Blood or no, Vaemond, I will not have you stoke mutiny.
如果你不尽力去掌控这场战争 大人
If you do not seize control of this war, my lord
我们所有人早晚会葬身蟹腹
the crabs will soon dine on all of us.
戴蒙王子
Prince Daemon.
我带来了韦塞里斯·坦格利安一世陛下
I bring word from His Grace, Viserys Targaryen First of His Name,
安达尔人 洛伊拿人和先民的国王
King of the Andals, the Rhoynar and the First Men
七国统治者暨全境守护者的旨意
Lord of the Seven Kingdoms, and Protector of the Realm.
够了！
That's enough!
停下！
Stop!
弟弟……
Brother...
我已下令派出十艘船
I have ordered ten ships
以及2000兵力 即刻从君临出发
and 2,000 men to set sail from King's Landing
为石阶列岛的战斗出力
to join the effort in the Stepstones.
尽管机缘使我们彼此疏远
Though time and circumstance have seen us estranged
要知道 我不希望看到你的行动失败
know that it is not my desire to see you fail in your course.
相反 我希望这次援助将带来
It is instead my hope that this aid will deliver the victory
迄今为止我们未能取得的胜利
that has thus far evaded us.
我将每晚向诸神祈祷你平安归来
I shall pray nightly to the gods for your safe return.
搭箭
Nock.
拉弓
Draw.
此为暗黑姐妹，坦格利安家族祖传宝剑之一，
由瓦雷利亚钢打造，曾为维桑尼亚·坦格利安（“征服者”伊耿的姐姐）的佩剑。
放箭！
Loose!
海烟
兰尼诺的龙
龙焰！
Dracarys!
搭箭！
Nock!
龙来了！
Dragon!
龙焰！
Dracarys!